Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on Students for a Democratic Society PE.035
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on Students for a Democratic Society
1959-1986
1960-1970
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
PE.035
7.35 Linear Feet in 6 record cartons, 3 shared boxes, and 1 flat file folder
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on Students for a Democratic Society (1959-1986, bulk 1960-1970) is an artificial collection, collected and assembled by the Tamiment Library over the course of several decades. The collection consists of printed ephemera such as event fliers, brochures, leaflets, pamphlets, and other publications, with the bulk of the materials dating from the early 1960s--when Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) operated under the auspices of the League for Industrial Democracy--through the 1970s. The collection documents the activities of the national organization and various local and regional SDS chapters, with materials that chronicle the group's strategic initiatives, actions, and the relationship between local chapters and the surrounding communities. The collection also contains pamphlets and publications from SDS-sponsored and allied projects, with a large amount of material from the Radical Education Project.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Custodial History
The provenance of the materials is varied. Items were obtained through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and through ongoing collecting by Tamiment staff.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Student League for Industrial Democracy (TAM 024)
Robert Bender: Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) Papers (TAM 409)
Students for a Democratic Society: James Zarichny Collection (TAM 517.1)
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series. Folders are arranged alphabetically within series. The series arrangement of the records is as follows:
Series I: National and Chapter Files, 1959-1986
Series II: Radical Education Project, 1963-1970
Historical Note
Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) was a radical student group born from the Student League for Industrial Democracy (SLID), which was the student branch of the League for Industrial Democracy (LID), a social democratic organization. The group was expelled from the LID in 1965 and gained national prominence in the late 1960s as the Students for a Democratic Society.
In 1962, SDS held its first national convention in Port Huron, Michigan, where the membership adopted the eponymous "Port Huron Statement" as its political manifesto. The manifesto was drafted by Tom Hayden, but convention members helped craft it into its final form. While not pro-Soviet Union, SDS did not take an anti-communist approach in their organizing activities. This issue led to trouble with the League for Industrial Democracy and an eventual split from the parent organization. SDS organized around numerous issues, including opposing the Vietnam War, the draft, and participatory democracy. In April 1965, SDS organized the March on Washington opposing the war in Vietnam, which drew tens of thousands of people and situated SDS nationally as one of the primary organizations of the New Left. Organizing around civil rights issues, SDS was inspired by the work of the Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee. SDS was primarily a campus organization, but began to spread to more community-oriented projects like the Economic Research and Action Project and Chicago JOIN projects.
During 1968, SDS experienced increased factionalism involving Progressive Labor (PL) members and the RYM I (Revolutionary Youth Movement) group, which advocated for a more student-oriented, militant, counter-cultural program. The June 1968 SDS National Convention was full of discord. PL supporters gained policy victories that stressed attempts to gain working-class support, but RYM I and other non-committed delegates continued to dominate the organization's leadership positions. SDS persevered and remained in the center of student protests like the Columbia University strike in the spring of 1968 and the activities at the Democratic National Convention that summer in Chicago.
After being at the forefront of the New Left during the 1960s, internal pressures surfaced again at the June 1969 National Convention. SDS split into three factions: PL, Weathermen, and RYM II. This latter group, composed of diverse, moderate SDSers, collapsed within a year due to its inability to develop a coherent activist program. The Weathermen, which included many of the national leaders and staff members, sought to initiate an immediate revolution; within six months, the organization had gone underground and its leaders were wanted in connection with mob violence and bombing. SDS-PL continues today as an off-shoot of the Progressive Labor Party.
Scope and Content Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on Students for a Democratic Society (1959-1986, bulk 1960-1970) consists of a selection of printed matter, including event fliers, pamphlets, brochures, newsletters, bulletins, and other publications, as well as constitutions, position papers, convention materials, and circular letters. The collection dates from 1959 to 1986, with the bulk of the materials dating from the early 1960s--when Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) operated under the auspices of the League for Industrial Democracy--through the 1970s.
The collection documents the activities of the national organization and various local and regional SDS chapters, with materials that chronicle the group's strategic initiatives, actions, and the relationship between local chapters and the surrounding communities. Major actions of SDS are represented in the collection, including its first official national convention at Port Huron, Michigan and the resulting political manifesto known as the "Port Huron Statement," as well as the March on Washington in April of 1965 opposing the Vietnam War. Notable chapters documented in the collection include several New York-based schools, such as New York University, Columbia University, Queens College, City College of New York, City University of New York, Brooklyn College, and Stony Brook University. The collection also contains pamphlets and publications from SDS-sponsored and allied projects, with a large amount of material from the Radical Education Project.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library. There is no accession record associated with this collection.
In 2025, materials from accession 2019.056, which is associated with Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on Subjects (PE 029), were transferred to this collection.
Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Protest movements -- United States.; Radicalism -- United States.; Radicals -- United States -- Civil rights; Anti-war demonstrations.; Student movements -- United States.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Protest movements.; Direct action -- United States.; Student movements -- New York (N.Y.); New Left -- United States.; Student movements.; Radicals -- United States.; Revolutionary Youth Movement II (SDS); Radical Education Project (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.)
- Series I: National and Chapter Files, 1959-1986; 6.1 Linear Feet in 5 record cartons, 2 shared manuscript boxes, and 1 flat file folder
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I: National and Chapter Files, dated 1959 to 1986, contains printed material published by the organization nationally while based out of San Francisco, Chicago, and Boston, as well as materials created by local and regional chapters of SDS from throughout the United States. These files document the national and local activities of SDS, identifying the ideologies of the group and showing how chapters interpreted and deployed the national organization's strategic initiatives in local communities. There are fliers for regional conferences, meetings, film screenings, sit-ins, teach-ins and strikes, as well as for more well known events like the 1965 March on Washington against the war in Vietnam. As the SDS was affiliated with the League for Industrial Democracy in the early 1960s, files from this period hold memoranda and correspondence from the parent organization.
  This series contains several files of pamphlets and publications that discuss the group's position on social and civic issues, including racial and socioeconomic inequality in the United States, and the influences of inequality on the Vietnam War draft. The authors are primarily past presidents, vice-presidents or executive secretaries. Pamphlets and publications are arranged first chronologically and then alphabetically based on either prominent subject or author.
  In addition to the printed matter that was put out nationally, material, if identified, is organized under local chapter or region. There are files from Amherst College, Harvard/Radcliff, Columbia University, New York University, Brooklyn College, Queens College, Stanford University, Yale University and the Madison, Wisconsin Branch, as well as the New England and New York Regionals. The files show the wide range of issues that concerned campus chapters, such as racial injustice in the community; wage inequality and layoffs in large local employers; disputes over course offerings and university initiatives; and the overarching issues of the national organization, such as protesting the Vietnam War. Local and regional chapter files may also contain chapter histories and campus or community news clippings that contextualize the environment in which the chapter was formed and in which it operated. Meeting minutes and publications of individual committees illuminate how the local chapters were goverened. Circular letters and fliers produced by the chapters also document dissonance between local chapters and the national organization.
  This series contains a few subject files with publications, pamphlets, fliers, and circular letters on major activities of SDS: anti-draft and anti-Vietnam War organizing, women's liberation and the organizations' joint civil rights work with the Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee (SNCC). Subject files provide a broad view of how SDS approached the core issues of its concern through both education and action. The splits that occurred within SDS at the 1969 National Convention in Chicago involving Progressive Labor and the Revolutionary Youth Movement II are documented in subject files.
  Projects sponsored by or allied with SDS are documented in this series as well. These projects include Chicago JOIN, the Economic Research and Action Project (ERAP), the Liberal Study Group, the Peace Research and Education Project, and the Worker Student Alliance. These files contain source materials SDS assembled or created to provide the intellectual basis for project goals and actions: background papers, conference working papers, bibliographies, and reprinted articles, which were distributed for educational outreach and constituency building.
  - 1960 Conference for Human Rights in the North (Box 1)
  - Amherst College Chapter (MA), 1965-1968 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Chapter (MI), circa 1968 (Box 1)
  - Anti-Draft Organizing, 1966-1968, undated (Box 1)
  - Berkeley Chapter (CA), undated (Box 1)
  - Bill Haywood Caucus, undated (Box 1)
  - Boston (MA), 1960-1973 (Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 192, Folder 19)
  - Boston State SDS, undated (Box 1)
  - Boston Summer Research Project, undated (Box 1)
  - Boston University (MA), 1969-1970, undated (Box 1)
  - Brandeis Chapter (MA), 1966-1968 (Box 1)
  - Brochures, 1965-1969 (Box 1)
  - Brochures: Cuba, undated (Box 1)
  - Brochures: Introductions to Students for a Democratic Society, 1963-1964, undated (Box 1)
  - Brooklyn College, CCNY, and CUNY Chapters (NY), 1969, undated (Box 1)
  - Bulletin I, 1963-1965 (Box 1)
  - Bulletin II, 1963-1965 (Box 1)
  - Bulletin (Discussion), 1964-1965, undated (Box 1)
  - Bulletin (Membership), 1962-1963 (Box 1)
  - "Calendar of Struggle", 1969 (Box 1)
  - CAW! (Magazine of Students for a Democratic Society): Publicity Materials, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Chapter Organizing: Manual and Roster, 1964, undated (Box 1)
  - Chapters (Various), 1966-1968, undated (Box 1)
  - Chicago Demonstration (October, 11, 1969) (Box 1)
  - Chicago Join, 1965-1966, undated (Box 1)
  - Columbia University/Barnard Chapter (NY) I, 1966-1969, undated (Box 1)
  - Columbia University/Barnard Chapter (NY) II, 1966-1969, undated (Box 1)
  - Columbia University/Barnard Chapter (NY) III, 1966-1969, undated (Box 1)
  - Columbia University/Barnard Chapter (NY): Committee of Correspondence, undated (Box 1)
  - Columbia University/Barnard Chapter (NY): Expansion Committee, undated (Box 1)
  - Columbia University/Barnard Chapter (NY): Morningside Housing Committee, circa 1969 (Box 1)
  - Columbia University/Barnard Chapter (NY): School of International Affairs/CIA Connection, undated (Box 1)
  - Columbia University/Barnard Chapter (NY): Strike Committee/Student Strike Coordinating Committee, 1968, undated (Box 1)
  - Columbia University/Barnard Chapter (NY): Summer Liberation School, undated (Box 1)
  - Community Union Project (Cleveland, OH), 1964-1966, undated (Box 1)
  - Conferences, 1960-1967, undated (Box 1)
  - Constitutions, 1959-1970 (Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 192, Folder 20)
  - Economic Research and Action Project I, 1962-1967, undated (Box 1)
  - Economic Research and Action Project II, 1962-1967, undated (Box 1)
  - Economic Research and Action Project: Pamphlets and Publications I, 1962-1967 (Box 1)
  - Economic Research and Action Project: Pamphlets and Publications II, 1962-1967 (Box 2)
  - Economic Research and Action Project: Pamphlets and Publications I, undated (Box 2)
  - Economic Research and Action Project: Pamphlets and Publications II, undated (Box 2)
  - Economic Research and Action Project: Pamphlets and Publications III, undated (Box 2)
  - Educational Packet, undated (Box 2)
  - Event Fliers (General or Unspecified Chapter), circa 1960-1973 (Box 2)
  - Fayetteville, Arkansas SDS, undated (Box 2)
  - Film Unit, undated (Box 2)
  - Freedom Draft Card, undated (Box 2)
  - Fundraising, undated (Box 2)
  - Handwriting on the Wall (serial), undated (Box 2, Flat-file-folder 2 Left)
  - Harvard/Radcliff Chapter (MA), undated (Box 2)
  - High School Students, 1968-1970, undated (Box 2)
  - House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC): Workshop and Protest, 1967, undated (Box 2)
  - Introduction to SDS, undated (Box 2)
  - Job Orientation In Neighborhoods (JOIN) (New York, NY), undated (Box 2)
  - John Brown Caucus, undated (Box 2)
  - Labor Committee, 1969, undated (Box 2)
  - Labor Committee (New York and Philadelphia), 1968 (Box 2)
  - Labor Committee (New York and Philadelphia), 1969, undated (Box 2)
  - Labor Committee (New York and Philadelphia), undated (Box 2)
  - League for Industrial Democracy: Memoranda and Reports, 1960-1962 (Box 2)
  - League for Industrial Democracy: Memoranda and Reports, 1962-1965, undated (Box 2)
  - Liberal Study Group, 1961-1965, undated (Box 2)
  - Liberal Study Group: Papers Prepared for National Student Congress, 1962-1963 (Box 2)
  - Literature Lists, 1963-1967, undated (Box 2)
  - Long Island University Chapter (NY), 1968, undated (Box 2)
  - Los Angeles SDS, undated (Box 2)
  - Madison Chapter (WI), 1968, undated (Box 2)
  - March on Washington, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Meetings: Agendas and Reports, 1961-1964 (Box 2)
  - Membership Card, undated (Box 2)
  - Memoranda and Correspondence, 1961-1962, undated (Box 2)
  - MIT Students for a Democratic Society (MA), 1969, undated (Box 2)
  - National Conventions (Affiliated with League for Industrial Democracy) (New York, NY), 1960 (Box 2)
  - National Conventions (Port Huron, MI), 1962 (Box 2)
  - National Conventions (Pine Hill, NY; Clear Lake, IA) I, 1963-1968 (Box 2)
  - National Conventions (Pine Hill, NY; Clear Lake, IA) II, 1963-1968 (Box 2)
  - National Conventions (Chicago, IL) I, 1969 (Box 2)
  - National Conventions (Chicago, IL) II, 1969 (Box 2)
  - National Conventions (Regional; Race), undated (Box 2)
  - National Conventions, undated (Box 2)
  - National Executive Committee, 1960 (Box 3)
  - National Office/ National Secretary/ National Council, 1964-1969, undated (Box 3, Box Shared Tamiment 192, Folder 21)
  - National Reunion (California State University, Long Beach), 1986 (Box 3)
  - National Student Labor Action Project (SLAP), undated (Box 3)
  - New England Regional I, 1965-1971, undated (Box 3)
  - New England Regional II, 1965-1971, undated (Box 3)
  - New Haven Chapter (CT), 1968, undated (Box 3)
  - New Jersey Region, undated (Box 3)
  - New Left Notes: Articles from and Material Related to, 1968-1973, undated (Box 3)
  - New York Region (New York, Niagara, Syracuse), 1960-1970 (Box 3)
  - New York University (NYU) Chapter, 1968-1969, undated (Box 3)
  - New York University (NYU) Chapter: Anti-Vietnam War/ROTC Organizing, 1968-1969, undated (Box 3)
  - New York University (NYU) Chapter: Dow Chemical Protests, 1967, undated (Box 3)
  - New York University (NYU) Chapter: Event Fliers, 1968-1970, undated (Box 3)
  - New York University (NYU) Chapter: Martin Luther King, Jr., Death of, 1968 (Box 3)
  - New York University (NYU) Chapter: Meetings (Fliers, Agendas and Structure Proposals), 1967-1968, undated (Box 3)
  - New York University (NYU) Chapter: Position Papers, undated (Box 3)
  - New York University (NYU) Chapter: Publications, 1968-1970, undated (Box 3)
  - New York University (NYU) Chapter: Student Worker Coalition/Strikes, 1968, undated (Box 3)
  - Newark Community Union Project (NJ), 1959-1968 (Box 3)
  - Newark Community Union Project (NJ), undated (Box 3)
  - Newsletters, 1965-1966 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1965-1970, undated (Box 3, Box Shared Tamiment 192, Folder 22)
  - Northeastern University Chapter (MA), 1968 (Box 3)
  - Oberlin Students for a Democratic Society (OH), circa 1966, undated (Box 3)
  - Officers and Staff Roster, undated (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and Publications I, 1962-1968 (Box 3, Box Shared Tamiment 192, Folder 23)
  - Pamphlets and Publications II, 1962-1965 (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and Publications, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and Publications, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Box Shared Tamiment 192, Folder 23)
  - Pamphlets and Publications, 1969-1972 (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and Publications I, undated (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and Publications II, undated (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and Publications: Booth, Paul, undated (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and Publications: Brown, Ray (Crisis Economy), undated (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and Publications: Davidson, Carl, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and Publications: Gitlin, Todd, 1963-1967 (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and Publications: Haber, Alan, 1962-1966, undated (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and Publications: Hayden, Tom, 1962-1966, undated (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and Publications: Kissinger, Clark, 1966, undated (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and Publications: Mills, C. Wright (Letter to the New Left), circa 1960 (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and Publications: Organizing Manuals, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and Publications: Race/Racism/Black Power, circa 1962-1969 (Box 4)
  - Pamphlets and Publications: Ross, Bob (Welfare State), 1966 (Box 4)
  - Peace Research and Education Project I, 1964-1965, undated (Box 4)
  - Peace Research and Education Project II, 1964-1965, undated (Box 4)
  - Peace Research and Education Project III, 1964-1965, undated (Box 4)
  - Political Education Project, undated (Box 4)
  - Port Huron Statement, 1962, 1964 (Box 4, Box Shared Tamiment 189, Folder 11)
  - Position Papers, 1962-1970 (Box 4)
  - Position Papers, undated (Box 4)
  - Position Papers (scrapbook of), undated (Box 4)
  - Press Releases, 1962-1968 (Box 4)
  - Program Proposals, 1968-1969, undated (Box 4)
  - Progressive Labor Party: Split with Students for a Democratic Society, 1967-1971 (Box 4)
  - Publications on, circa 1972-1976, undated (Box 4)
  - Queens College, 1969, undated (Box 4)
  - Radical Education Program, 1966, undated (Box 4)
  - Resolutions and Draft Proposals, 1966-1969, undated (Box 4)
  - Revolutionary Marxist Caucus, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
  - Revolutionary Youth Movement I (RYM I), 1968, undated (Box 4)
  - Revolutionary Youth Movement II (RYM II), 1969, undated (Box 4)
  - Revolutionary Youth Movement: Split with Students for a Democratic Society, 1969 (Box 4)
  - San Francisco (CA), 1963, undated (Box 4)
  - San Francisco State SDS, 1969, undated (Box 4)
  - Stanford University Chapter (CA), 1969, undated (Box 4)
  - Stony Brook, undated (Box 4)
  - Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee (SNCC): Memoranda and Reports, 1961-1968 (Box 4)
  - Swarthmore College Chapter (PA), 1963 (Box 4)
  - Temple Chapter, undated (Box 4)
  - Transit Project (New York, NY), 1968, undated (Box 4)
  - University Committee, 1965 (Box 4)
  - University of California, Los Angeles Chapter, 1970 (Box 4)
  - University of Chicago Chapter (IL), undated (Box 4)
  - University of Houston SDS, undated (Box 4)
  - University of Illinois, Chicago, 1966 (Box 4)
  - Vietnam/Anti-Vietnam War Organizing I, 1964-1969, undated (Box 4)
  - Vietnam/Anti-Vietnam War Organizing II, 1964-1969, undated (Box 4)
  - Vietnam/Anti-Vietnam War Organizing: March on Washington (April 17, 1965) (Box 4)
  - Vietnam/Anti-Vietnam War Organizing: Publications, 1965-1967, undated (Box 4)
  - Women's Liberation, 1972, undated (Box 5)
  - Work-in Organizers' Manual, undated (Box 5)
  - Worker Student Alliance (Various Chapters), 1968-1969 (Box 5)
  - Worklist Mailings, 1963 (Box 5)
  - Worklist Mailings, 1964 (Box 5)
  - Worklist Mailings I, 1965 (Box 5)
  - Worklist Mailings II, 1965 (Box 5)
  - Yale University Chapter (CT), 1968-1969, undated (Box 5)
- Series II: Radical Education Project Publications, 1963-1970; 1.75 Linear Feet in 1 record carton, 1 shared manuscript box, and 1 shared oversize box
  Series II: Radical Education Project Publications dates from 1963 to 1970 and consists of the pamphlets and publications distributed by the Radical Education Project, a sponsored project of the SDS. The Radical Education Project was created for internal education in the New Left movement as well as outreach to members of society at large, and its publications were intended to provide an intellectual support to the programs and theories of the movement. While many of the subjects mirror those covered in general SDS publications (such as women's liberation and draft resistance), the Radical Education Project Publications are broader in scope than SDS publications found in Series I, and were intended to be distrubuted to a larger audience than the SDS membership.
  The pamphlets and publications are arranged by subject. This series also contains literature lists, circular letters and memoranda, reports and proposals and brief introductions to the Radical Education Project in the form of brochures and pamphlets. The pamphlets in this series are generally published out of Ann Arbor, Michigan, but occasionally out of Detroit. This series contains one file of material from the Bay Area Radical Education Project, based out of San Francisco, CA.
  - About and Background Information on the Radical Education Project: Brochures and Pamphlets, 1966-1968 (Box 5)
  - Bay Area Radical Education Project (San Francisco, CA), 1966-1970, undated (Box 5)
  - Circular Letters and Memoranda, 1967-1969, undated (Box 5, Box Shared Tamiment 189, Folder 11)